A Guide to the Publications of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1947-1997
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Separate Publications
  - Bristol, Roger Pattrell. Index of Printers, Publishers, and Booksellers Indicated by Charles Evans in His American Bibliography. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1961. iv, 172 pp., 1961.1
    Plain brown dust jacket. "Printed on Standard Permalife Text, 70 pound basis, at the University of Virginia Press, November 1961."
  - Castillo, Homero, and Raul Silva Castro. Bibliography of the Chilean Novel / Historia Bibliografica de la novela chilena. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia; Mexico City: Ediciones de Andrea, 1961. 214, [1] pp., 1961.2
    "Six hundred copies of this work have been produced, two hundred and twenty-five of which have been bound.... The co-publishers, Ediciones de Andrea of Mexico City, are the exclusive distributors of the paper bound copies. Printed in Mexico, 1961. [rule] Impreso en los Telleres `Impresora Dante' de la Ciudad de Mexico." Paperbound form issued as #28 in the series "Coleccion Studium."
  - McKenzie, D. F. Stationers' Company Apprentices 1605- 1640. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1961. [10], 178 [1] pp., 1961.3
    Plain brown dust jacket. "Seven hundred and fifty copies printed by the University of Virginia Press on Permalife paper."
  - Morrison, Paul G. Index of Printers, Publishers and Booksellers in A. W. Pollard and G. R. Redgrave A Short-Title Catalogue of Books Printed in England, Scotland & Ireland and of English Books Printed Abroad 1475- 1640. A Second Impression offset from the Secretary's Copy, with a Few Corrections Written in by Hand. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1961. [2], 82 pp., 1961.4
    To the request in 1950.3 for corrections, a handwritten note now adds: "[Still welcome. 1961]". 920 copies.
  - Mummendey, Richard. Belles Lettres of the United States of America in German Translations: A Bibliography / Die schone Literature der vereinigten Staaten von Amerika in deutschen Ubersetzungen: Eine Bibliographie. (Bonner Beitrage zur Bibliotheks- und Bucherkunde, ed. Richard Mummendey, no. 5.) Bonn: H. Bouvier u. Co., Publishers; Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1961. xi, [1], 199, [3] pp., 1961.5
  - Bear, James A., Jr., and Mary Caperton Bear. A Checklist of Virginia Almanacs, 1732-1850. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1962. [2], xliv, [209] pp., 1962.1
    Glassine dust jacket. "Printed by lithography at the University of Virginia Press from photocopy prepared by the authors. The paper is Warren's No. 66. The binding is by the Albrecht Company of Baltimore."
  - Bristol, Roger P. Evans' American Bibliography: Supplement (Checking Edition). Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1962-64., 1962.2
    Twenty-two photo-offset and stapled fascicles of 32 pages and a final one of 29 pages issued from 1962 through December 1964 to spur identification of additional items not in Evans. A leaf containing only p. 466 was issued separately to correct errors on the original in fascicle 15. Based in part on contributions in
    16 (Feb. 1951), 19 (Sept. 1951), 27 (July 1953), 28 (Sept. 1953), 32 (Feb. 1955), 37 (Sept. 1957), 38 (Feb. 1958); collected as 1965.1; responses in
    52 (Aug. 1966), 53 (Dec. 1967); formally published as 1970.2.
  - Cevasco, George A. J. K. Huysmans in England and America: A Bibliographical Study. [Charlottesville]: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, [1962]. 30 pp., 1962.3
    Loose in stiff paper wrappers.
  - Henley, Elton F. A Check List of Masters' Theses in the United States on William Wordsworth. [Charlottesville]: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, [1962]. i, [1], 29, [12] pp., 1962.4
  - Marco, Guy A. The Earliest Music Printers of Continental Europe: A Checklist of Facsimiles Illustrating Their Work. [Charlottesville]: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, [1962]. 20 pp., 1962.5
  - Allen, Reginald. W. S. Gilbert: An Anniversary Survey and Exhibition Checklist with Thirty-Five Illustrations. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1963. [8], 82, [2] pp., 1963.1
    Glassine dust jacket. Includes "W. S. Gilbert: An Anniversary Survey," reprinted from
    Theatre Notebook
    15.4 (Summer 1961), and "The Grolier Club W. S. Gilbert Exhibition Checklist" (for 11 September-7 October 1961). "Manufactured in the United States of America | The Allen Company, Incorporated | Charlottesville, Virginia"; "Photographic copies by Ralph Claar, Pierpont Morgan Library, New York." 969 copies.
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. II, Part i: Introductions to the Padua Measure for Measure, The Winter's Tale; Collations. Part ii: Text of the Padua Measure for Measure, The Winter's Tale. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1963. [4], 29; [31] pp., 1963.2
    Parts in stiff paper wrappers, together in portfolio within slipcase. "Part ii of the Padua
    Measure for Measure
    and
    The Winter's Tale
    was printed by The Meriden Gravure Company under the supervision of E. Harold Hugo and John F. Peckham on Arches heavyweight laid ivory paper. The title page, its verso, the captions and the colophon were printed letterpress and the pages of the First Folio were reproduced by collotype." For a description of the series see 1960.2; for electronic edition see 1997.2.
  - Lacy, William S., Jr., ed. Index to "The Commonwealth" Volumes 1- 20 (1934-1953). Foreword by J[ohn] C[ook] W[yllie] for V[irginia] L[ibrary] A[ssociation]. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1963. [4], 33 pp., 1963.3
    Green stiff paper covers, with tape spine. Index to the magazine of the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce.
  - O'Neal, William B. Charles Smith: His Work in Book Design: A Checklist. Secretary's News Sheet 50 (July 1963)., 1963.4
  - Bloomfield, B. C. W. H. Auden: A Bibliography. The Early Years through 1955. Foreword by W. H. Auden. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1964. xix, [3], 171, [2] pp., 1964.1
    W. H. Auden: A Bibliography
    was composed and printed by The William Byrd Press, Richmond, Virginia, for the University Press of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia. Types used are Linotype and Monotype Granjon with Monotype Garamont display. Paper is Permalife Text made by Standard Paper Maufacturing Company. Binding is by Moore and Company, Inc. The book was designed by John J. Walklet, Jr." For second edition see 1972.2.
  - Blotner, Joseph. William Faulkner's Library A Catalogue. Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, Published in Cooperation with Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1964. x, 142, [3] pp., 1964.2
    William Faulkner's Library A Catalogue
    was composed and printed by The William Byrd Press, Inc., Richmond, Virginia. The types used are Linotype Caledonia and Ludlow Bodoni Black. The paper is Oxford Eggshell made by the Oxford Paper Company. Binding is by Moore & Co., Inc., Baltimore, Maryland. The book was designed by John J. Walklet, Jr." 1065 copies.
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. III, Part i: Introduction to the `Nursery' The Comedy of Errors, Midsummer Night's Dream; Collations. Part ii: Text of the `Nursery' The Comedy of Errors, Midsummer Night's Dream(Sigs. N1 v, N5 N1 v). Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1964. [4], 35; [19] pp., 1964.3
    Parts in stiff paper wrappers, together in portfolio within slipcase. "Part ii of the `Nursery'
    The Comedy of Errors
    Midsummer Night's Dream
    was printed by The Meriden Gravure Company under the supervision of E. Harold Hugo and John F. Peckham on Arches heavyweight laid ivory paper. The title page, its verso, the captions and the colophon were printed letterpress and the pages of the First Folio were reproduced by collotype." For a description of the series see 1960.2; for electronic edition see 1997.2. 518 copies.
  - Kelly, William W. Ellen Glasgow: A Bibliography, ed. Oliver L. Steele. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1964. xl, 330 pp., 1964.4
    Presswork by University of Virginia Printing Office. 620 copies.
  - Bristol, Roger P. Evans' American Bibliography: Supplement (Checking Edition). Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, [1965]. vii, 731, [2] pp., 1965.1
    A bound cumulation of twenty-three mimeographed fascicles issued from 1962 through December 1964 (entry 1962.2), with new "Introduction to the Bound Edition" signed December 15, 1965, and "Identification of Bibliographical Citations." "This volume... takes no account of the thousands of bits of correctional information now in hand. It is simply the Checking Edition, which is now issued in bound form for use until the final printed volume is issued, presumably several years hence [see 1970.2]." Page 466 stamped "CANCELLED | SEE NEXT LEAF" and a new page 466 bound in.
  - Silver, Rollo G. Typefounding in America, 1787- 1825. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1965. xiii, [1], 139, [2] pp., 1965.2
    Glassine dust jacket. "
    Typefounding in America, 1787-1825
    by Rollo G. Silver was composed by Connecticut Printers, Inc., Hartford, Connecticut, printed by The Meriden Gravure Company, Meriden, Connecticut, and bound by Russell-Rutter Company, Inc., New York, New York. Illustrations are by The Meriden Gravure Company. The paper is Mohawk Superfine. The types are Monticello and Bulmer. Design is by Edward Foss." 2062 copies.
  - (Tanselle, G. Thomas. The Historiography of American Literary Publishing. [Charlottesville]: University Press of Virginia, [1965]. 39 pp., 1965.3
    Self paper wrappers. "Reprinted from
    , XVIII (1965), 3-39." Four leaves reprinting the preliminaries of
    18 and originally appearing between the cover and the beginning of the article were cancelled before publication. Distributed by University Press of Virginia, including to members of the Publishers' Lunch Club and of the Association of American University Presses. 200 copies.)
  - Christophers, Richard A. George Abbot, Archbishop of Canterbury, 1562-1633: A Bibliography. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1966. xxiv, 211, [1] pp., 1966.1
    878 copies.
  - Dameron, J. Lasley. Edgar Allan Poe: A Checklist of Criticism 1942- 1960. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1966. 159 pp., 1966.2
    Stapled gatherings; no covering.
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. IV, Part i: Introduction to the Smock Alley Hamlet Collations. Part ii: Text of the Smock Alley Hamlet. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1966. [4], 48; [32] pp., 1966.3
    Parts in stiff paper wrappers, together in portfolio within slipcase. For a description of the series see 1960.2; for electronic edition see 1997.2. 510 copies.
  - Franklin, Rosemary F. An Index to Henry James's Prefaces to the New York Edition. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1966. [2], 29 pp., 1966.4
    Self paper wrappers.
  - Heaney, Howell J., and Rudolf Hirsch, eds. Selective Check Lists of Bibliographical Scholarship, Series B: 1956-1962. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1966. [8], 247 pp., 1966.5
    Plain brown dust jacket. Presswork by University of Virginia Printing Office; binding by The Albrecht Co., Baltimore. "The Selective Check Lists of Bibliographical Scholarship for 1956 through 1962 are reprinted here from
    , Volumes XI-XVII, with the addition of an index of authors and subjects." 982 copies.
  - Kaser, David, ed. Books in America's Past: Essays Honoring Rudolph H. Gjelsness. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1966. x, [4], 279, [1] pp., 1966.6
    Books in America's Past
    | Essays Honoring Rudolph H. Gjelsness | was composed, printed, and bound by Kingsport Press, Inc., Kingsport, Tennessee. The types are Baskerville and Bulmer, and the paper is Warren's Olde Style. Design is by Edward G. Foss."
  - Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography [Part 1]. Secretary's News Sheet 52 (August 1966)., 1966.7
  - Aljure-Chalela, Simon. Jose Eusebio Caro: Bibliografia. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. v, [1], 82 pp., 1967.1
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report."
  - Harding, Walter. Emerson's Library. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. xi, [1], 338 pp., 1967.2
    1297 copies.
  - Hawthorne, Nathaniel. Poems, ed. Richard E. Peck. [Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967.] x, [2], 34, [1] pp., 1967.3
    Poems
    was composed by The Composing Room, Inc., New York, New York, and was printed and bound by Kingsport Press, Inc., Kingsport, Tennessee in an edition of 750 copies. The type is Palatino, designed by Hermann Zapf. The end sheets are Tumba Ingres, supplied by Andrews/Nelson/Whitehead, and the cover paper is Curtis' Tweedweave. The text paper is Mohawk's Superfine. Designer: Edward G. Foss. General Editor: Walker Cowen." Selected for Southern Books Competition 1967. 747 copies.
  - Heilbronner, Walter L. Printing and the Book in Fifteenth-Century England. Preface by Curt F. Buhler. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1967. xiv, 105 pp., 1967.4
    997 copies.
  - Henry, William H., Jr. A French Bibliography of W. Somerset Maugham: A List of His Works Published in France, His Contributions to French Periodicals, the Swiss, Belgian, and French Criticism of His Books, Plays, and Films. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. [2], vii, [1], 133 pp., 1967.5
  - Jones, Gordon W. The Library of James Monroe (1758-1831), 5th President (1816-1824) of the United States. Fredericksburg, Va: James Monroe Museum and Memorial Library; Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. 65 pp., 1967.6
    Self paper wrappers; "The issuing in near-print of a manuscript designed ultimately for book form... ." 500 of the copies distributed by the James Monroe Memorial Foundation.
  - Mish, Charles C. English Prose Fiction, 1600-1700: A Chronological Checklist. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. 110 pp., 1967.7
    "The present checklist, like its mimeographed predecessor of 1952 [1952.4, 5, 6], is basically a chronological rearrangement of the seventeenth-century material in Arundell Esdaile's
    List of English Tales and Prose Romances Printed Before 1740
    (London, 1912)." ?1000 copies.
  - Silver, Rollo G. The American Printer 1787-1825. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1967. xii, [2], 189, [1] pp., 1967.8
    The American Printer, 1787-1825
    was composed, printed, and bound by Kingsport Press, Inc., Kingsport, Tennessee. The plates were printed by The Meriden Gravure Co., Meriden, Connecticut. The type is Monticello, with Scotch Roman for the initials. The paper is Mohawk Superfine. Design is by Edward G. Foss." 2000 copies.
  - Stagg, Louis Charles. An Index to the Figurative Language of John Webster's Tragedies. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. iv, [2], 58 pp., 1967.9
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report"; "the first of a series of seven studies of the figurative language of the tragedies of Shakespeare's seventeenth-century contemporaries."
  - Stagg, Louis Charles. Index to the Figurative Language of Ben Jonson's Tragedies. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. [8], 47 pp., 1967.10
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report"; "the second in a seven-part series on the tragedies of Shakespeare's seventeenth-century contemporaries."
  - Stagg, Louis Charles. An Index to the Figurative Language of Thomas Heywood's Tragedies. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. [8], 54 pp., 1967.11
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report"; "the third in a series of seven studies of the tragedies of Shakespeare's seventeenth-century contemporaries."
  - Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography [Part 2]. Secretary's News Sheet 53 (December 1967)., 1967.12
  - Tutwiler, Carrington C., Jr. Ellen Glasgow's Library. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. 31 pp., 1967.13
    Self-paper wrappers.
  - Williams, Franklin B., Jr. Photo-Facsimiles of STC Books: A Cautionary Check List. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1967. [2], [22 ("109-130")] pp., 1967.14
    Self paper wrappers. Reprinted from
    21 (1968), 109-130.
  - Davis, Arthur Kyle, Jr. Matthew Arnold's Letters: A Descriptive Checklist. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1968. xlv, [1], 429 pp., 1968.1
    1041 copies.
  - Ferguson, W. Craig. Valentine Simmes: Printer to Drayton, Shakespeare, Chapman, Greene, Dekker, Middleton, Daniel, Jonson, Marlowe, Marston, Heywood, and Other Elizabethan s. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1968. [2], 113 pp., 1968.2
  - Massey, Linton R. "Man Working," 1919-1962: William Faulkner. A Catalogue of the William Faulkner Collections at the University of Virginia. Introduction by John Cook Wyllie. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, distributed by University Press of Virginia, 1968. x, [6], 250 pp., 1968.3
    Composition, presswork, and binding by Kingsport Press. 1554 copies.
  - Spalek, John M. Ernst Toller and His Critics: A Bibliography. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, distributed by University Press of Virginia, 1968. xxii, 919 pp., 1968.4
    Glassine dust jacket. "The bibliography was prepared for photo-offset by Marcella Curtright of Gardena, California." Presswork and binding by Valley Offset, Deposit, N.Y. 571 copies.
  - Tanselle, G. Thomas. The Descriptive Bibliography of American Authors. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, [1968]. 24 pp., 1968.5
    Stiff paper wrappers. "[R]eprinted from
    Volume Twenty-One, 1968," pp. 1-24. 500 copies, for the U.S. Copyright Office. The order was in error for 1969.4, and apparently all copies except 25 sent to the author were destroyed.
  - Walker, Ursula Genung. Notes on Theodore Roethke. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1968. [6], 52, [1] pp., 1968.6
  - Barrow, Robert M. Advertising Cuts from the Virginia Gazette, 1754-1770. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1969. [2], 8, [6] pp., 1969.1
  - Crane, Stephen. The Notebook of Stephen Crane, ed. Donald J. Greiner and Ellen B. Greiner. [Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1969.] xxi, [1], 76 pp., 1969.2
    Composition, presswork, and binding by Kingsport Press, Kingsport, Tenn. "A John Cook Wyllie Memorial Publication." 750 copies.
  - Fry, Donald K. Beowulf and The Fight at Finnsburh: A Bibliography. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1969. xx, 222 pp., 1969.3
    Composition and presswork by Science Press, Ephrata, Pa. 1509 copies.
  - Tanselle, G. Thomas. Copyright Records and the Bibliographer. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, [1969]. [48 ("77-124")] pp., 1969.4
    Stiff paper wrappers. "Reprinted from
    , Volume Twenty-Two, 1969 [pp. 77-124]." 400 copies, for the U.S. Copyright Office.
  - Tutwiler, Carrington C., Jr. A Catalogue of the Library of Ellen Glasgow. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1969. [6], xvii, [1], 287 pp., 1969.5
    Stiff paper wrappers. A "Technical Report." 300 copies.
  - Arnold, A. James. Paul Valery and His Critics: A Bibliography. French-Language Criticism 1890-1927. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1970. xxii, 617 pp., 1970.1
    571 copies.
  - Bristol, Roger P. Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography. Charlottesville: For the Bibliographical Society of America and Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1970. xix, [1], 636 pp., 1970.2
    The final version of 1965.1. Index published as 1971.1. 1946 copies.
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. V, Part i: Introduction to the Smock Alley Macbeth; Collations. Part ii: Text of the Smock Alley Macbeth. Charlottesville: A Publication of Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia | University Press of Virginia, 1970. [4], 36; [23] pp., 1970.3
    Parts in stiff paper wrappers, together in portfolio within slipcase. For a description of the series see 1960.2; for electronic edition see 1997.2. 554 copies.
  - Stagg, Louis Charles. An Index to the Figurative Language of George Chapman's Tragedies. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1970. [6], 143 pp., 1970.4
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report"; "the fourth in a seven-part series on the tragedies of Shakespeare's seventeenth-century contemporaries." 250 copies.
  - Stagg, Louis Charles. An Index to the Figurative Language of Cyril Tourneur's Tragedies. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1970. [6], 44 pp., 1970.5
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report"; "the fifth in a seven-part series on the tragedies of Shakespeare's seventeenth-century contemporaries."
  - Stagg, Louis Charles. An Index to the Figurative Language of Thomas Middleton's Tragedies. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1970. [6], 65 pp., 1970.6
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report"; "the sixth in a seven-part series of studies on the tragedies of Shakespeare's seventeenth-century contemporaries."
  - Stagg, Louis Charles. An Index to the Figurative Language of John Marston's Tragedies. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1970. [6], 86 pp., 1970.7
    Self paper wrappers. A "Technical Report"; "the seventh and last in a series of studies of the imagery in the tragedies of Shakespeare's seventeenth century contemporaries."
  - Bristol, Roger Pattrell. Index to Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography. Charlottesville: For Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia by University Press of Virginia, 1971. [10], 191 pp., 1971.1
    "Save for possible addenda to the
    Supplement